[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is the simile of wet wood, wet timber.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose there were a wet, sappy piece of timber lying in the water and a man were to come along with the upper fire stick thinking, I'll light a fire, I'll produce heat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would he be able to light a fire and produce heat by rubbing the upper fire stick in the wet, sappy timber lying in the wood?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the timber is wet.
[SPEAKER_00]: And besides, it is laying in the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, the man will reap only his share of weariness and disappointment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Buddha says, so it is with contemplatives who do not live withdrawn from sensuality in body and mind, and whose desire, infatuation and fever for sensuality is not relinquished and stilled within him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether or not he feels painful, wracking, piercing feelings due to his striving for awakening, he is incapable of knowledge and vision and self-awakening.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no matter how intense many different virtues you keep or and how painful it is, how sensuous strange you are,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, if you're not... if you're not devaluing the sensuality, if you're still valuing it, holding on to it as a valuable thing, if you're not seeing the danger from in it, means you are still with that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're not engaging in it, if you're just torturing yourself, not eating, maybe, like, not just drinking water and so on, you're still doing that with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it doesn't matter the extent of that endurance, it will not result in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: As you said previously with
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be secluded from music, and lovely food, or whatever, and people.
[SPEAKER_00]: And being in an empty room, but you're delighting in the prospect that once you leave this room, you're gonna, you know, you're gonna taste this lovely food and you're gonna see some people, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... so you will never get... Yeah, so then your abstinence is temporary.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means the overall framework of sensuality remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not relinquishing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might be playing with it and restraining yourself for whatever reason, but overall, the value of centrality remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean when I said before, like, when you do keep the virtue and practice sense restraint and have this enduring, you have to do it with the attitude, oh, I will do this infinitely, forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how long this lasts, I will have to endure it forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, I'll do this for a week.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, then I'll most likely go back to the same value of sensual and chasing pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you're not free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you haven't endured enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might have already endured more than enough for wisdom to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the wisdom won't arise, because overall you're not relinquishing the value of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you haven't endured sufficiently.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just continue with this simile.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose there were a wet, sappy piece of timber lying on the land, far from the water, and a man were to come along with an upper fire stick, thinking, I'll light that fire and produce heat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would he be able to light a fire and produce heat by rubbing that upper stick, upper fire stick, with the wet, sappy timber lying on land, far from water?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the timber is wet and sappy, even though it is lying on land.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly what you just said, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though you are secluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not in the water anymore, but the mind is still wet with the value of centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what you're doing, how much effort you're putting, how motionless, for how many hours you sit in your samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have not, on the level of your views, devalued sensuality forever, you are still within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there will be no wisdom arising on account of whatever practice you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it keeps us going.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the third part of the ceremony.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose there were a dry, sapless piece of timber lying on land, far from water, and a man were to come along with the upper fire stick, thinking, I'll light that fire and produce heat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would he be able to produce that heat?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, Master Gautama, because that timber is dry and sapless and it is lying on the land far from water.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he would probably be able to do it with little effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the effort is pretty much determined how wood... how wet the wood is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Determines how much... how hard you have to rub the sticks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: How dry it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's damp, still you have to... you have to do it even harder and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's really, really dry...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you actually invest your effort in drying the sticks, then it's going to take very little physical effort to light the fire with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Often, like, we often repeat that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter whether you're a monk or a layperson.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to practice the dhamma, practically speaking, most of the work comes down to drying your mind from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't come down to finding a perfect technique or reading the exact sutta that will make you enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why you're not enlightened, even after you read all the suttas, it's not because you haven't read enough suttas or you haven't thought about them enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because your sticks were not dry enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's always... and again, it's not... it's not accidental, that that's always that something which is being overlooked.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the... that's why essentiality is hard to get rid of, because it's easy to overlook it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sense restraint is already the practice of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue is already the practice of dhamma, because you're already drawing the sticks.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, by the way, if sometimes people wonder, you know, you read the suttas and a man is mentioned there, he just heard one sentence from the Buddha and became enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people just assume, oh, he was so lucky, it was the Buddha's special powers made him enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the Buddha said himself, I cannot make anyone enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: I point the way, they either choose to follow it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the Tathāgata can do is point the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So how did then that man get enlightened after one sentence?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you realize, if you actually read closer or read other suttas, oh yeah, his mind was very dry.
[SPEAKER_01]: He spent years of quite a secluded practice, withdrawn from sensuality, obviously devaluing sensuality thoroughly, because otherwise one sentence from the Buddha would have not been enough for enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, when you read thousands of sentences from the Buddha and you're not enlightened, it's not because you read them wrongly or because they're different sentences.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because your sticks are wet.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't light the fire because you're not withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's when, practically speaking, most of the work, especially for a lay person who wants to practice dhamma without becoming a monk, is about withdrawing from sensuality in the lay world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is doable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean easy or pleasant, but doable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the worst possible thing to do, is to tell, oh, you don't have to withdraw from sensuality, and you can practice for the fire, that the Buddha says it's impossible, for as long as you don't dry the sticks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just keep practicing, and sticks will magically become dry, and the fire of wisdom will arise, and we will all be happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And works the opposite, as the Buddha described.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the effort you're going to put in lighting the fire with wet sticks, will go to waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you haven't... you have not dried the sticks.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will only... reap despair and frustration.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, withdrawal from sensuality, sustaining the mind withdrawn from sensuality, it's not just doable, it's what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Becoming immovable in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you might be one of those people that needed only one sentence for the right view and enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you did the extra work of drying your sticks from centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've done 80% of the work already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most people would be coming to the dhamma, to practice the dhamma, with genuine reasons, with serious determination, but at the same time, still not completely devaluing that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still thinking that they don't need to devalue sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but I don't have to, because I'm not a monk, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why all the effort and all determination they have, will not result in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all you need to do is read a sutta like that, and it just says it clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the necessary prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, if you complete that prerequisite of living withdrawn from sensuality,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will need very little effort to light the sticks.
[SPEAKER_00]: As it says, it says, So it is with contemplatives who live withdrawn from sensuality in body and mind, and whose desire, infatuation and fever for sensuality is relinquished, and still within him, whether or not he feels painful, piercing feelings due to his striving, he is capable of knowledge and vision and self-awakening.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very little.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the work is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always comes to mind that...
[SPEAKER_01]: I forgot the name of that layman in the sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was obviously practicing dhamma before, and I think multiple times he's seen the Buddha, and eventually he even was was freeing himself from sensuality, and went back home and said to his wives that it's unsuitable for me to engage in sexual intercourse with you now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not becoming a monk or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but, you know, I did take you on as my wives.
[SPEAKER_01]: I promised I'll look after you, so I will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any of you who wants to stay or get remarried, let me know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll arrange everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, I'll look after you for the rest of my life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'll be celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: I cannot not be celibate.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not suitable for me to not be celibate, having understood the dhamma to the extent I did.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he took on that as a normal behavior, because, you know, that's where the work is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abstaining from sensuality, keeping the sticks dry, that is resulting in wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even a little instruction from the Sutta, let alone all the Tipitakas we have now, in 15 different translations, and original Pālis, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, if your sticks are dry, you need maybe 10% of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will start seeing things clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible not to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are actually doing the work on the level that it matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said when we started this, sensuality, that's like mentally abandoning sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, oh, I won't think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means devaluing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you step out, you step physically outside of the puddle of sensuality, the lake, the swamp of sensuality, but mentally you still value that water.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mentally, you're not withdrawn from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might be living on top of mountains, secluded from from sensual distractions, but mentally, you still value pleasure of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see the peril infinitely, forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, mentally, you are not withdrawn from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start contemplating the infinite peril, mentally, let alone physically, you are withdrawing yourself mentally as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, things from the suttas will just start falling into place, much more than before.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you just do one rub, and there is already smoke, and fire started, because you dried the sticks properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what I'm trying to point out is that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, it's obviously a subtle thing, so people can easily misunderstand what mental withdrawal from sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just, I will never think these sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might present themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's whether you value, delight, entertain, indulge them mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see the danger?
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing the danger, automatically, you're making yourself withdraw from those values, from those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you withdrawn?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you're not seeing the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't decide, I will mentally withdraw myself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that mind is already in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can make your mind withdraw itself from it, by seeing the danger in that which it values.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will never see the danger in that which you value, if you think you don't have to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think you're exempted from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think sensuality is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think sensuality is not your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think because you're not a monk, you don't need to address these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you want to practice dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter whether you're a monk or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sticks need to be dry.